Register of the African subject collection, 1831-2007
Hoover Institution Archives
African subject collection,
1831-2007.
XX762
40 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 3 phonorecords, 1 phonotape cassette, 6 videotape cassettes (14.6 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Electronic and other bulletins, pamphlets, leaflets, clippings, serial issues, reports, communiqués, press releases, maps, and other printed matter, relating to various aspects of twentieth-century African history; political, social and economic conditions in Africa as a whole; revolutionary movements in Africa; international support groups for such movements; droughts and famines in the Sahel region and elsewhere; and the AIDS epidemic in Africa.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives. An increment was added in 2011.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Content of Collection
Electronic and other bulletins, pamphlets, leaflets, clippings, serial issues, reports, communiqués, press releases, maps, and other printed matter, relating to various aspects of twentieth-century African history; political, social and economic conditions in Africa as a whole; revolutionary movements in Africa; international support groups for such movements; droughts and famines in the Sahel region and elsewhere; and the AIDS epidemic in Africa.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Droughts--Africa.; Africa--Famines.; Africa--History.; Africa--Politics and government--1960-; Phonorecords.; Phonotapes.; Video tapes.; Africa--Economic conditions--1960-; Africa--Social conditions--1960-; Guerrillas--Africa.; AIDS (Disease)--Africa.
Collection Contents
- GENERAL SUBJECT FILE, 1902-1995. (Box 1-12)
  Electronic and other bulletins, pamphlets, leaflets, clippings, serial issues, reports, press releases, maps, and other printed matter, relating to various aspects of twentieth-century African history; political, social and economic conditions in Africa as a whole; revolutionary movements in Africa; international support groups for such movements; droughts and famines in the Sahel region and elsewhere; and the AIDS epidemic in Africa.
- DROUGHT AND FAMINE, 1970-1995. (Box 13-16)
  Announcements, articles, clippings, pamphlets, press releases and reports relating to drought conditions throughout Africa
- REVOLUTIONARY MOVEMENTS, 1962-1995. (Box 16-17)
  Articles, bulletins, clippings, communiques, newsletters, statements and reports relating to revolutionary movements in Africa
- MISCELLANEOUS FILE, 1987-1995. (Box 17)
  Brochures, clippings, leaflets, pamphlets and printed matter relating to various aspects of life in Africa
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS, 1989. (Box 18)
  French Revolution Bicentennial postcards and posters
- AUDIO-VISUAL FILE, 1967-1987. (Tape cabinet, Record cabinet, Cassette cabinet)
  6 videocassette tapes, 3 phonorecords and 1 phonotape cassette relating to African culture
Container List
See card catalog for increments that may have been received after February 1995
- GENERAL SUBJECT FILE, 1902-1995
  - General (Box 1)
    - General
    - Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome (AIDS)
      - General
      - Clippings
        - 1986
        - 1987-1991 (Box 2)
      - Newsletter
      - Reports
        - General
        - Countries
          - Botswana
          - Cameroon
          - Central African Republic
          - Congo
          - Cubans in Africa
          - Gabon
          - Ghana
          - Guinea-Bissau
          - Ivory Coast
          - Kenya
          - Lesotho (Box 3)
          - Liberia
          - Malawi
          - Mauritius
          - Namibia
          - Niger
          - Nigeria
          - Rwanda
          - Senegal
          - South Africa
          - Soviets in Africa
          - Sudan
          - Swaziland
          - Tanzania
          - Uganda
          - Zaire
          - Zambia
          - Zimbabwe
    - Arab Bank for Economic Development in Africa
    - Bibliography on decentralization policies
    - Communism
    - Conference and seminar papers
    - Conference and seminar papers (Box 4)
    - East Africa
    - Equatorial Guinea
    - Economics
      - General
      - Economic Community of West African States (ECOWAS)
      - Group of African, Carribean and Pacific States - Relations with the European Economic Community
      - Women's World Banking
    - Education
    - Female circumcision
    - Foreign relations
      - General
      - Canada
      - United States
    - French West Africa (Box 5)
    - Politics
      - General
      - Organization of African Unity
      - Refugees
    - Southern Africa
    - Southern African Development Coordination Conference (SADCC)
  - Sub-Saharan Africa
    - West Africa
  - International support groups
    - General
      - General
      - Student groups
    - Africa 2000
    - Africa Inland Mission (AIM)
    - African-American Institute (Box 6)
    - African Medical and Research Foundation (AMREF)
    - Aktionskomitee Afrika
    - All African People's Revolutionary Party
    - All African Students Union in Australia
    - American-African Affairs Association
    - American Committee on Africa
      - General. Includes materials on southern Africa, primarily Namibia, Angola and Guinea-Bissau; and Portugal
        - 1955-1958
        - 1961-1975
        - 1976-1978
        - 1979-1983
        - 1984-1987
      - Africa Fund. Includes materials on countries of southern Africa and divestment (Box 7)
        - General
        - 1972-1982
        - 1972-1982
        - 1983-1994
      - Bibliography
      - Committee to Oppose Bank Loans to South Africa (COBLSA)
        - General
        - Oakland branch
        - San Francisco branch
      - Reports. Includes materials on Africa in general
      - Statements
      - United States Congress. Congressional testimonies. Includes material on United States- Portuguese relations in Africa
    - American Friends Service Committee (Box 8)
      - General. Includes newsletters, memoranda and flyers relating to southern Africa
      - Committee to Oppose Bank Loans to South Africa (COBLSA). See American Committee on Africa
      - News clippings packages. Includes materials on southern Africa
        - 1977
          - June-September
          - September-November
        - 1978
          - January-March
          - April
    - Amnesty International
    - Association of Concerned Africa Scholars
    - Australian Center for International Agricultural Research
    - Bay Area Anti-Apartheid Network
    - Bikes for Africa
    - Boston Southern Africa Alliance
    - British Defence and Aid Fund for Southern Africa
    - Campaign to Stop the War against Angola and Mozambique (SWAM)
    - Center for the Study of Power and Peace
    - Committee for Academic Freedom in Africa
    - Coordinating Committee for International Voluntary Services (CCIVS)
    - D.C. Coalition Against Apartheid and Racism
    - D.E.F.A. Research (Box 9)
    - Deutsches Komitee fur Angola, Guinea-Bissua und Mocambique
    - Europe/Africa Research Project
    - Foundation for African Arts
    - Freedom House
    - Freedom Rising Africa Solidarity Committee
    - Informationszentrum Dritte Welt
    - International Society for Individual Liberty, Inc.
    - International Society for Human Rights
    - Lutheran World Ministries
    - National Coalition to Support African Liberation
    - Osterreichischer Informationsdienst fur Entwicklungspolitik
    - Oxfam
    - Peace Corps
    - Saint Charles Lwanga African Academy, Inc.
    - Save the Children
    - Secretariat of the International Union of Students
    - Third World Forum
    - Toronto Committee for the Liberation of Southern Africa
    - United Nations
      - General
      - Centre Against Apartheid (Box 10)
      - Children's Education Fund
      - Food and Agricultural Organization (FAO)
      - General Assembly
      - Office of Public Information
      - Permanent missions to the United Nations
      - Reports
      - Special Committee Against Apartheid
      - Sport Aid
      - World Health Organization
    - United States Student Association
    - Unitarian Universalist Service Committee
    - Verlag Arbeiterkampf
    - Voix Plurielle
    - Washington Office on Africa
      - 1971-1979
      - 1980-1985 (Box 11)
      - 1986-1994
    - Miscellany
      - Algeria
      - Burundi
      - Cape Verde
      - Central African Republic
      - Djibouti
      - Equatorial Guinea
      - Gabon
      - Libya (Box 12)
      - Madagascar
      - Morocco
      - Rwanda
      - Sao Tome and Principe
      - Seychelles
      - Sudan
      - Western Sahara
- DROUGHT AND FAMINE, 1970-1995
  - General (Box 13)
  - Africare
  - Appeals for aid
  - Bibliography
  - Clippings and articles
  - Comite Permanent Interetats de Lutte Contre la Secheresse dans le Sahel (CILSS)
  - Interreligious Foundation for Community Organization (IFCO)
  - League of Red Cross and Red Crescent Societies (Box 14)
    - Announcement of monetary gifts to the League
      - 1975-1978
      - 1979-1982
    - Clippings and articles
    - Fund raising
      - 1980-1983
      - 1984-1988
    - Newsletter, Panorama
    - Press releases
    - Printed matter
    - Reports
      - 1973
      - 1974-1977
      - 1978-1981 (Box 15)
      - 1982-1983
      - 1984-1988
  - Sahel
    - Appeal for aid
    - Bibliographies and research guides
    - Clippings and articles
    - Pamphlets
    - Press releases
    - Reports
  - United States. Congressional hearings
  - Stanford East African Relief Organization (SEARO) (Box 16)
  - Sudan
  - United Nations
    - General
    - Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO)
  - United States. Agency for International Development (USAID)
- REVOLUTIONARY MOVEMENTS, 1962-1995
  - General. Directories of African revolutionary movements and international support groups (Box 16)
  - Federazione Student Africani in Italia
  - Canary Islands. Mouvement pour l'Autodetermination et l'Independance de l'Archipel Canarien (MPAIAC)
  - Cape Verde. Partido Africano da Independencia de Cabo Verde (PAICV)
  - Comoro Islands. Mouvement de Liberation Nationale des Comores (MOLINACO)
  - Djibouti. Union des Mouvements Democratiques (Box 17)
  - Morocco. Polisario
  - Portuguese colonies
    - General
    - Committee for Freedom in Mozambique, Angola and Guinea-Bissau
    - Frente Patriotica de Libertacao Nacional (FPLN)
    - Movimento Popular Anti-Colonial (MPAC)
  - Sudan
  - Swaziland
- MISCELLANEOUS FILE, 1987-1995
  - Brochure (Box 17)
  - Clippings
  - Leaflets
  - Pamphlets
  - Printed matter
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS, 1989
  - Reunion. French Revolution Bicentennial postcards and posters (in French) (Box 18)
- AUDIO-VISUAL FILE, 1967-1987
  - Videotape cassettes (Tape-cabinet Tape cabinet)
    - Live Aid Concert. Fund raising for African famine relief, n.d. Four tapes, VHS
    - Sport Aid. UNICEF. Promotional package, 1986. One tape, VHS
    - Sport Aid. UNICEF. TV special, parts 1-3, 1986. One tape, VHS
  - Phonorecords (Record-cabinet Record cabinet)
    - A.F.R.I.C.A. Stetsasonic, 1987 "Africa in Revolutionary Music," 1967
    - Africare, 1979
  - Phonotape cassette. "Chaque Homme Est Mon Frere," Buhendwa Nachiko, 1986 (Cassette-cabinet Cassette cabinet)
- Incremental Materials (Box 19-41)
  This addition to the collection has not yet been described. Please let the Hoover Institution Archives know if you would like to see this material described.